If you dove into the Sun... the first layer you'd
hit is hot enough to make diamonds boil. If you
keep going, you're passing through churning
bubbles the size of France. And then you're
lost in a zone so dense that light itself
takes 170,000 years to escape... and you're
still not at the place where it unleashes enough
energy to power... all life on Earth. Right now,
we're in a golden age of new solar science.
We're getting close-up pictures of the Sun's
surface in more detail than ever before,
sending probes into its atmosphere and
revealing secrets about our star we never
thought possible. Trust me, after this video,
you'll never look up at the Sun the same way.
So, let me take you on a journey... into the Sun.
This episode was made possible by AT&T, the
official connectivity partner of HUGE* If True.
A lot of people picture the Sun as a giant ball of
fire, but that's totally wrong. There's nothing
actually burning up there. Imagine you and I get
into a magical spaceship and blast off toward
the Sun. As soon as we get about six times Earth'sdiameter away, our little ship is starting to
detect something. We think we're on a journey
into the Sun. But really... is it true to say that
in some sense we are inside the Sun right now? "Oh,100%." That is the head of heliophysics at NASA.
He'sin charge of all of NASA's research on the Sun.And he's saying if you zoom out to see our
wholesolar system and then zoom a little bit further,you'd see that our Sun's outer atmosphere
actuallyswallows Earth and then keeps going. This isthe heliosphere and it's huge. It goes about
100 times farther than the distance between Earthand the Sun. "We are living not just
with a star, but living in a star's atmosphere, which ispretty cool." As we fly through it, we see that
the heliosphere is made of the Sun blasting out
these charged particles more and more as we fly
toward it. From here, we can see so much cool tech
that humans have sent to study the Sun before us.
We already passed around 40 satellites orbiting
Earth, studying the Sun. And now we're speeding
past a very special one. This is the Solar
Dynamics Observatory. It's snapping pictures of
the Sun in all these different wavelengths. "It's
one of the biggest data sets that we have at NASA
and it's frankly the beating heart of watching the
Sun every day and its activity and its changes."
But we keep going closer and there are still two
spacecraft ahead of us. "The two of them are Solar
Orbiter and Parker Solar Probe." Solar Orbiter is
a big deal because it took the first-ever pictures
of the Sun's south pole. For scale, here's how
big the Earth would be in this video.
But only one spacecraft has ever gone into the Sun's inner
atmosphere. At this point, our little ship is
starting to feel more of the Sun's effects. Uh,
that can't be good. But we need to keep going
because the Sun is way farther away than most
people think. If you paused the whole solar system
at the closest point with a normal walking pace,
it would take you over 3,000 years to reach the
Sun. You could line up all of the planets between
the Earth and the Sun 374 times. But it's not
just the distance that's the problem. The Earth is
rapidly moving sideways compared to the Sun. So to
get there, we have to cancel that out, which would
take more energy than it would take to escape the
entire solar system. That's why when NASA sent
the Parker Solar Probe, it took over six years
to spiral inward until 2021 when it crossed into
the corona. This is the Sun's inner atmosphere.
It's the part that you see during a solar eclipse,
and it's beautiful! But up close... it's terrifying.
When Parker first crossed into it, the probe
was still about nine times farther from the
Sun than the Sun itself is wide. But Parker's
been making passes closer and closer, faster
and faster ever since. It's now the fastest
object humans have ever made. It could get from
London to Paris in two seconds. But funny enough,
the scientists who made it don't actually like
that. "And I don't like it. I would like it to
slow down. I want Parker to spend as much time
as possible very close to the Sun so we can get
all the wealth of the data." The data suggests
that our Sun's corona is over 1 million °C. How is
the Parker Solar Probe not melting? "In some sense,
this is not a real temperature. To actually
feel the heat, you're going to need a lot more
particles." Turns out that commonly cited number
is sort of a lie. The charged particles that make
up the corona are moving insanely fast. And how
fast particles are moving is what we're really
measuring when we say temperature. But lucky for
Parker, there are very few of those particles. In
fact, so few that the scientists who built Parker
don't really care about these particles that much.
"We are not worried about it. We can actually sneak
our instruments into that flow and it doesn't do
anything." The heat they do worry about is the
same heat and energy that we use here on Earth,
which comes from the light itself. "The only thing
that really hurts Parker is when the solar surface
heat, like this big radiating lamp, uh, can
shine directly on the sensitive parts." Light,
or more specifically, photons, carries the Sun's
energy across the vacuum of space toward us. But
this close, sunlight is hundreds of times more
intense than it is on Earth. That's why Parker
hides all of its scientific equipment behind
this very thick heat shield. "They would do these
demos on this carbon-carbon composite. You take
a blowtorch and you would hold it there as long
as you wanted and then ask everybody to touch the
back of the darn thing and the back was ice cold."
As it flew through the corona, Parker recorded
something incredible. Sounds coming from the Sun.
There were these chirping sounds and this
weird sound and these hissing sounds. But
if you're thinking, "Hey, you can't hear
things in space. There's no air." You're
right. These sounds are actually electric and
magnetic waves that scientists then converted
into sound waves. They're the sounds of intense
solar wind from those same charged particles
that the Sun is constantly blasting out to
create the heliosphere. The whooshing sound
comes from changes in the speed of
that solar wind. The layered pitches
represent changes in the temperature. When
it gets hotter, the pitch gets higher. And
when there's a particularly big explosion
called a solar storm, everything gets louder.
Those solar storms can get really dangerous
for us on Earth. And scientists today say
that we should be getting ready for a big one
soon. In 1859, the Sun released a large blast
of particles that shot out and raced toward the
Earth. It took under a day to travel over 150
million km and slam into our planet, causing the
largest solar storm ever recorded. It resulted in
dark red northern lights that could be seen
as far as the tropics. Luckily, on Earth,
life is protected by our own magnetic field.
It deflects most of those charged particles.
So these storms don't affect life on Earth,
but they do affect technology. "In 1967,
it almost caused a nuclear war." Really?! "Yeah, so there was this huge storm. The US found its
radars in, you know, northern Greenland jammed.
They thought the Soviets had jammed. Fortunately,
the US Air Force already had a solar physics
group which could quickly say that no, no, no,
put the planes back on standby." The Sun goes
through cycles of activity that last about 11
years. If the Sun cycle is at the top of this
graph, it basically means that it's throwing a
tantrum. It's got flares and eruptions and storms,
lots of charged particles coming at us. If it's
at the bottom, it's basically napping. Today,
we're about here and we've been seeing visible
signs of it. "Quite frightening, isn't it?" That's
one reason why studying the Sun is so crucial,
both for our future on Earth and for our future
in space. Because on the Moon or Mars, there's
no strong magnetic field to hide behind. So
off-world, these storms could mean dangerous doses
of radiation. "We're going to establish a moon
base. We're going to put boots on Mars. I want
to be able to tell them, you can go on Expedition
X for this many hours, days, and be able to
say with confidence that they're going to be able
to do that without risking their lives." The Parker
Solar Probe could only get here, but our ship
is magically protected. So, we're going deeper.
As our ship approaches the surface,
we notice something very weird. Wait,
why is it getting colder? To go further,
it's time to breach the surface of the
Sun. This is the photosphere. Particles
here are moving slower, so it's actually
a cooler temperature. Here, the temperature
is 5,500 °C. Hot enough to boil diamonds. So,
atoms are getting ripped apart into plasma. And
all around you "...is boiling and roiling bubbles of
gas constantly moving." And we just got the most
detailed look ever. These extreme close-ups were
taken by the newest and most powerful solar
ground telescope in the world. What's truly
crazy is the scale in these images. You could
fit the entire Earth right... here. In this photo,
each of these bubbles is the size of France. And
sometimes you might see... a sunspot darker, cooler,
and wider than our whole planet. And in 1795,
these sunspots led to a bit of confusion. So,
one of the most famous astronomers at the time,
Sir William Herschel, wrote this paper that said
that sunspots might be openings that reveal the
Sun has a solid surface that could be inhabited
by the Sun people. Now, we know that these
sunspots are actually cooler patches where the
Sun's magnetic field is so strong it's choking off
the heat rising from below. So, no Sun people. But
with our protected craft, we're still going deeper
through the photosphere into the convective zone.
This is a boiling ocean of plasma rising and
cooling and sinking like a giant churning pot.
The motion is similar to our own mantle inside
Earth. But where that's a slow-moving solid, this
is a fast-moving superheated gas. Now the heat is
rising again back up to 2 million°. And inside our
little ship, we feel this. There are a lot more
atoms hitting us now. But as we travel inward,
suddenly everything stops. Hello? "You go about
30% inside the Sun and then the gas ceases to
flow." From the surface of the Sun to us back on
Earth, light, or photons travel straight through
the vacuum of space in an 8-minute and 20-second
journey. But in here, the plasma is so dense that
light itself gets trapped, bouncing around like
a pinball machine that takes on average 170,000
years to escape. So when you step outside and
you feel the Sun on your face, that energy has
been traveling since before humans wore clothes.
We're now lost in the radiative zone. But wait,
if the closest we've ever been to the Sun was way
out there in the corona, how do we know what's
going on way down in here? That is her job. "You
know, there are people who study earthquakes and
use earthquakes to study the Earth. I use quakes
on the Sun to study what's happening inside." So,
when there's an earthquake on our planet, it
sends pressure waves down through the Earth
that act differently depending on what they're
moving through. So scientists collect data on
the surface to understand what's in between. Same
idea in the Sun, but instead of earthquakes, it's...
music. "Think of a drum." So these violent boiling
outer layers of the Sun are constantly jiggling
the inside parts with pressure waves like
earthquakes through the Earth. And the
jiggles of pressure waves is also called sound.
"The Sun is a musical instrument that plays many,
many notes." If we could hear the music, the
different notes would tell us what the waves
were traveling through. The problem is that
we're 150 million km away with a big vacuum
in between that sound can't travel through. So,
it's more like "...there's a drum playing in a sound
uh soundproof room. If you have a good enough
instrument, you'll see the surface of the drum
moving even if you don't hear it. And by analyzing
how the surface of the drum moves, you can figure
out the tones and overtones." The boiling motion
of the Sun makes sound that travels through it,
jiggling the surface just a little bit. And then
scientists look at how the color of the light
shifts bluer as the surface moves towards us and
redder as it moves away. And then translate that
with math into what must be in the middle
of the Sun. So the boiling of the outer
layers creates sound waves inside the Sun which
jiggles the surface which we can then see from
150 million km away with using red and blue
light to see how it moves on the surface and
then use math to translate what must be
inside the middle of the Sun. Oh my God,
it's so complicated and so cool and they call it
helioseismology. But what if we go... deeper? Now we're
finally entering the core. The pressure around us
now is equivalent to about 250 billion of Earth's
atmosphere. The stuff right outside our ship is
13 times denser than lead. But it's so hot that
even something that dense is still not solid.
And if you could zoom into this plasma to see
the bare hydrogen nuclei inside, you'd see them
smashing together. Four hydrogen nuclei go in,
one helium atom comes out that weighs just a
tiny bit less, about 0.7% becomes energy. This
is nuclear fusion and it is the source of all of
the Sun's energy. About 600 million metric tons
of hydrogen fused into helium every second with
4 million tons of matter converted straight into
energy. Those numbers sound huge because they are.
But what's really weird is in terms of how much
energy is generated per cubic meter. The Sun's
output is actually tiny. It's roughly similar
to a lizard's metabolism. Your body, pound for pound
generates more energy than the core of the Sun.
But the Sun is way bigger than you think. How
many Earths do you think you could fit inside
the Sun? Assume you keep them round? 960,000. And
if you melted them to get rid of the extra space,
1.3 million. But what happens when one day our Sun
uses up all of its fuel? When will our Sun die? Is
it halfway through its lifetime? Is it near the
end? Well, you can map out all of the stars that
we've ever seen, and you'd get this famous chart
showing the stars' birth to death. The Sun is now
here, where it'll spend most of its life. As stars
like ours age, the core uses up its hydrogen fuel
and then shrinks, creating heat and pressure that
push the outer layers outward, growing into a red
giant. It'll get so big it'll engulf Mercury and
Venus and maybe even Earth. Then about a billion
years after that, it'll use up all its helium
fuel and collapse into a white dwarf, cooling
and dimming over billions more years. Is the Sun a
teenager? Is the Sun a middle-aged person? "It's a
middle-aged star. It's 4.5 billion years
old." And now we are at the very center of our Sun,
the middle of the biggest thing in our solar
system that powers all life we know about.
There's still a lot that we don't know about the
Sun. Like why the 11-year cycle? "Nobody knows or
understands why that is." "Our knowledge of solar
activity and how it impacts us on the Earth is
skin deep." "It's a puzzle with a solution, but which
we don't know the solution yet." But what we do
know is the result of so much human work. So the
next time you go out and you look up at the Sun...
"Think about where that photon came from.
I think about that and it just gives me
immense joy." And remember that we're a tiny
species on a tiny rock orbiting a star we
owe everything to. And so we figured out how
to send probes and listen to its music and take
unbelievable pictures to protect ourselves from
it and slowly reveal its mysteries. HUGE* If True.
If you want there to be more
optimistic science and tech
stories, subscribe to support our
show, HUGE* If True. And remember,
this episode was made possible by AT&T,
the official connectivity partner of HUGE* If True.